Guide to the McLaughlin Air Service Photograph Collection 1934-1969 (bulk 1940-1942) PR 43
New-York Historical Society
McLaughlin Air Service Photograph Collection
1934-1969 (bulk 1940-1942)
New-York Historical Society
PR 43
2.73 Linear feet (7 boxes)
Aerial views of the five boroughs of New York City. Prints date from 1941-1942.
Provenance
Purchase, 1972
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Historical Note
The McLaughlin Air Service Company was a Manhattan-based aerial photography service.
Scope and Content Note
The McLaughlin Air Service Photograph Collection spans the period from 1934-1969 and contains aerial photographs of New York City and surrounding areas. The bulk of the photographs were taken between 1940 and 1942, before the spurt of post-World War II development.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series:
Missing Title
Series I. Prints
Series II. Negatives
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other aerial views of New York City can be found in the Thomas Airviews Collection (PR 106).
Separated Material
Negatives in Series II are cellulose nitrate and are kept in cold storage. Please see a reference librarian if you feel you need access to these negatives.
Bridges -- New York (State) -- New York.; Tunnels -- New York (State) -- New York.; Roads -- New York (State) -- New York.; Railroads -- New York (State) -- New York -- Yards.; Airports -- New York (State) -- New York.; Ocean liners; Waterfronts -- New Jersey.; Waterfronts -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; Queens (New York, N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; Photographic prints.; negatives (photographs); Aerial photographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Franklin D. Roosevelt East River Drive (New York, N.Y.); Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.) -- Description and travel.; New Jersey -- Description and travel.; Staten Island (New York, N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; La Guardia Airport; New York Central Railroad Company; Normandie (Steamship)
- Series I: Prints
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I contains 75 silver gelatin photographs. All are 5 x 7 inches, black and white, aerial views of New York City boroughs. These photographs record the city before it underwent its post-World War II development. Urban geography patterns stand out as do such features as bridges, tunnels, roads, and housing projects.
  Photographs are filed alphabetically by borough, and alphabetically by neighborhood or location therein. Manhattan images are filed moving north along the east side of the island, then north along the west side of the island, followed by interior views. Some photographs are specifically identified on the verso. Untitled general aerial views are not described.
  - BRONX
    - Mott Haven/rail yards (2 prints), 1941 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Yankee Stadium (2 prints), 1941 May 1 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - General aerial views (2 prints), 1941 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - BROOKLYN
    - Dyker Heights Golf Course and Belt Parkway (2 prints), 1941 June 9 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Sheepshead Bay (2 prints), 1941 June 9 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Williamsburg Bridge approach (2 prints), 1941 June 9 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - MANHATTAN
    - Manhattan Bridge approaches (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Battery Park and lower Manhattan (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Williamsburg Bridge approach (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - East Side, 10-30th Sts. (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - East Side piers (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - East Side, 23-14th Sts. (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - East Side including Chrysler Building (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Queensboro Bridge and Roosevelt Island (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - East Side and Roosevelt Island, 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - East Side, 80-110th Sts. (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Marcus Garvey Park and Triboro Bridge (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - West Side piers, Lower Manhattan (1print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - West Side piers west of Greenwich Village (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - West Side piers and Chelsea rail yards (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - West Side Piers, midtown (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Riverside Park (3 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - George Washington Bridge (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fort Tryon Park (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Inwood Hill Park (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Top of Manhattan, subway yards (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - University Heights Bridge (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - High Bridge Park (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Morningside Park (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    - Central Park and West Side (4 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    - Central Park and East Side (4 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    - Empire State Building and midtown (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    - Midtown, Herald Square to Times Square (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    - Midtown, Madison Square to Herald Square (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    - West Side (2 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Union Square (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Greenwich Village (3 prints), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bowery Street and Lower East Side (1 print), 1942 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - QUEENS
    - Kew Gardens Hills (1 print), 1941 Apr 21 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - General aerial views (3 prints), 1941 Apr 21 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - General aerial views (3 prints), 1941 Apr 28 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
      Scope and Contents
      One view shows Flushing Meadows-Crotona Park.
- Series II: Negatives
  Series II contains 807 negatives, both 5 x 7 and 8 x 10 inches. Manhattan is photographed in a systematic way, from East to West and North to South, missing very little. Also included are photographs of large ocean liners, including the Normandie, in port along the West Side of Manhattan. Images of the Bronx focus on parkland, new highways, and large housing projects. Photographs of Queens date from the building of many of that borough's planned neighborhoods and towns. The Belt Parkway is well documented along its route from Brooklyn to Queens, as are the neighborhoods it runs through. LaGuardia Airport and the grounds of the 1939-1940 World's Fair also appear in many shots. The routes of the West Shore Railroad, north from New Jersey into New York along the West Shore of the Hudson River, and of the New York Central Railroad Putnam Division, going north from the Bronx along the East side of the Hudson, are also photographed.
  Most of these negatives are cellulose nitrate film, and are thus stored in a freezer for preservation reasons. Researchers who need to utilize these negatives should contact a staff member for assistance.
  An inventory of the negatives can be found in the repository.